你好,学生
hello students
欢迎来到基础系列的视频
welcome to yet another entry in our fundamental series
今天我们讨论汇编
today we'll be talking about assembly code
还记得我在讲计算机体系结构时
if you recall when i talked about computer architecture
我给你们看的这张关于电脑的示意图吗
i showed you this diagram of what more or less a computer is
我说了
and i made the statement that
CPU关注的
everything that the cpu concerns itself with
只有二进制指令
is binary code instructions
不管你最初用什么语言写的代码
no matter what you originally write your code in
C, Python，够疯的话，甚至是Ruby
C Python even Ruby if you're a crazy person
最终CPU上运行的都是二进制指令
etc right and then you're gonna end up running binary instructions on a cpu
CPU基本只接受汇编作为它的指定语言
and that cpu basically only accept assembly as its true programming language
汇编基本就表示了二进制代码
so assembly is a programming language representation of basically binary code
它俩是非常直接的映射关系
very straightforward mapping
我们将讨论汇编语言中的几个概念
we're going to talk about several concepts in assembly language
这门课你们需要知道三个主要的
really three main ones that you need to know for this course
指令、寄存器和内存
instructions registers and memory
再次提醒大家
again as a reminder
这个基本系列应该是一个回顾
this fundamental series is supposed to be a review
也许能填补你知识上的一些小空白
maybe fill it some small gap you have in the knowledge
如果这对你是全新的
if this is really new material to you
那你还没准备好上这门课
then you are not ready to approach this course
你应该在上课前先学习汇编
and you should go learn that before taking it
熟悉的话，我们开始吧
otherwise let's roll
我们从寄存器开始
we actually started with registers
寄存器是非常快
registers are essentially very very fast
非常临时以及昂贵的存储数据的地方
very very temporary and very very expensive places to store your data
这个昂贵是字面上的钱上的贵
i say expensive as in literally the financial sense
它们在CPU里
they're right there in the cpu
它们要占用空间
they take up space
需要与环境连接上
they need to be connected to everything
很难设计
they're very hard to design in
所以历史上
and so historically there have been very very
设计时，它们一直很短缺
there's been a shortage of them in architecture designs
如果你回顾过去
if you go back in time
很旧之前
if you go way back in time
常看到早期架构中只有2个寄存器
you frequently see early architectures with like two registers
8085出现的时候
the 8085 when it came around
它是一个8位的架构
it was an 8 bit architecture
它是现代AMD64架构
that is the precursor to the precursor to
前身的前身
yeah the precursor to the precursor to the
的前身
precursor to the modern AMD64 architecture
可能说的还是不准
i probably still screwed that up
但无论如何，它是X86，以及amd64的祖先
but anyways it was an ancestor of X86 of AMD64 specifically
它有7个8位的通用寄存器
and it had seven general purpose 8 bit registers
Intel创建8086时，被扩展为16位
that were all extended and modified a little bit to 16 bit when Intel created 8086
他们把这7个8位寄存器
so they took all these 7 8 bit registers
扩展成了8个16位寄存器
they ended up with 8 general purpose 16 bit registers
从寄存器A变成了寄存器AX
so you went from A register A to register AX
X表示扩展
which is A eXtended
后面x86出现了
then x86 came around
并进一步扩展到32位
and extended it further to 32 bit
从AX变成了EAX
right and you went from ax to eax
我猜是Extended A eXtended
i guess Extended A eXtended
只是猜测，别引用
that's a guess don't quote me on that
再从32位的X86到AMD64
you went from X86 with 32 bits to AMD 64
AMD沿用了英特尔的架构
AMD took intels architecture
又增加了额外32位
and kind of put an extra 32 bits in it
并创建了amd64
and created amd64
还增加了寄存器的数量
they also extended the amount of registers that we have all together
就有了RAX
and then you have like Really extended A rax
arm架构也是
arm also
有很多寄存器
a lot of registers
同样的概念
same sort of concepts
其他架构，MIPS等
other architectures mips etc
通用寄存器用于保存通用数据
general purpose registers are there to hold general data
其中一些也有稍微特定的用途
some of them have also slightly specific purposes
像加粗的sp
the stack pointers that are bold
加粗的bp
and the frame pointers that are bold
amd64中的RSP RBP，我们稍后会提到
so RSP RBP in amd64 we'll talk about them in a second
还有arm上的R13与R14
and on arm r13 and r14
都提供相同的功能
serve the same function
还有特殊用途的寄存器
there's also special registers with special tasks
例如
for example
amd64中的RIP
rip is the Really extended Instruction Pointer on amd64
arm上的R15
r15 on arm
这里存储着下一条指令的地址
that's where the address of the next instruction is stored
这样CPU就知道去哪里拿
so that the cpu can retrieve it
一般来说
generally speaking
不会直接与这些指令寄存器交互
you don't interact with these instructions directly
但这也看
although that varies
是否直接与这些寄存器交互
the level of direct interaction with these registers
例如指令寄存器
like the instruction point registers
因架构而异
varies by architecture
还有各种扩展
there are also various extensions
添加了其他专用寄存器
that add other specialized registers
很早的时候，x87曾是x86的协处理器
x87 used to be a coprocessor to the x86 in the very early days
它增加了浮点数
that added floating point
支持了浮点寄存器和操作之类的
support floating point registers and operations and so forth
多媒体扩展
multimedia extensions
增加了大量更大的寄存器来执行复杂的操作
added tons of larger registers to do complex operations
在现代机器中
in a modern machine
在现代64位intel或amd的处理器中
in a modern 64 bit intel or amd processor
寄存器的大小可以达到512位
you have registers that are up to like 512 bits in size
这很疯狂
it's pretty crazy stuff
但是这里主要关注通用寄存器
but we'll focus here mostly on the general purpose registers
在接下来的课程中
and actually in the rest of the class
主要关注64位AMD/Intel架构
we will focus mostly on 64 bit AMD/Intel Architecture
这些通用寄存器
these general purpose registers
顺便说一下，可以只访问一个寄存器中的部分
by the way can all be accessed partially
例如 rax
you have a register rax
可以用eax访问它的低32位
you can access its lower 32 bits using eax
这也是为什么我会介绍其发展历史
that's why i went through the whole history lesson of course
不只是为了好玩
not just for fun
虽然是很有趣
although it is fun
可以用ax访问低16位
you can access the lower 16 bits using ax
用al访问低8位
can access the lower 8 bits using al
用ah访问低16位中的高8位
and then the higher 8 bits using ah or slightly higher
如幻灯片所示
like it shows on the slide
这是由于历史原因
due to a historical oddity
向后兼容
backwards compatibility
AMD在开发AMD64时做的一个选择就是
a choice made by AMD when they were creating AMD64 is that
以任何方式访问eax
accessing eax in any way
修改它，将清除rax的前32位
modifying it will wipe out the top 32 bits of rax
这很烦人
this is annoying
因为用ax、ah或al修改，都不会这样
because it doesn't hold true for ax or ah or al
你可以直接用它们，不会改动rax其余部分
you can access those independently without messing up the rest of the register
这非常烦人
it's extremely annoying
你将至少要花一个小时
and you will spend at least one hour of your life
对着电脑大喊大叫
screaming at your computer
因为你的shellcode不起作用
because your shellcode doesn't work
或你的rop chain不起作用
or your rop chain doesn't work
或别的什么，只是因为你忘了这一点
or something only to realize that you forgot about that
所以要做好准备
so just be ready
rax不是唯一一个可以部分访问的
rax isn't the only one that can be partially accessed
通用寄存器或多或少都可以部分访问
more or less every general purpose register can be partially accessed
但只有 a、c、d和b
but only acd and b
rax、rcx等等
rax rcx and so forth
可以访问低16位的高8位
can be accessed with their the high byte of the low 16 bits
很好，这些是寄存器
cool so those are registers
这是我们临时存储数据的地方
that's where we store our data temporarily
当寄存器用完的时候
again when we run out of registers
能用的寄存器越少，就越常发生
which happens more frequently  the less registers you have to work with
你就得把数据放到内存中了
you have to spill them out to memory
这个过程很烦
which is an annoying process
但编译器会帮你做好
but the compiler does all this for you
除非你要手写汇编
unless you're handcrafting assembly
我们来谈谈指令吧
let's talk about instructions
指令告诉CPU要做什么
instructions tell the cpu what to do
它们通常有几种不同的形式
and they generally they take several different forms
我们一会儿会讲指令类型
which we'll talk about individual instruction types in a second
通常他们有一个操作符与几个操作数
but generally they have an operator and several operands
我们以后会讲到这些
so we'll talk about all these in the future size
但我要介绍一个有用的参考文档
but i'll point out a useful reference
就是这个线上的x86汇编列表
is this online x86 assembly listing
这很酷
which is very cool
你可以看到指令
you can see the instructions
它们长什么样
you can see what they look like
和实际的二进制与16进制值
in terms of the actual binary and hexadecimal values
我们来看看指令类型
so let's roll with instruction types
类型1：数据操作
type number 1 data manipulation
这很直接
this is a fairly straightforward
我看到了一个令人尴尬的错误
i just saw a very embarrassing mistake on here
但我们就坚持看一下
but we're gonna power through anyways
后面会指出这个错误
i'll get to the embarrassing mistake all right
有几种不同的操作数据的方法
so a couple of different ways to manipulate data
有很多很多不同的方式
many many different ways
我就举几个例子
i'll go through a couple as high level examples
这里就是个复习
again this should be review
你应该能找出幻灯片上的错误
you should have spotted the mistake on this slide
如果没有，就先学习一下汇编
if you didn't go learn more assembly
简单说一下
as a quick note
这里的一切
everything here
以及这门课的所有内容
and everything in this course
将使用英特尔汇编语法
is going to be using Intel assembly syntax for amd64
有两种汇编语法
there are two assembly syntaxes
一个合适
one is correct
一个不合适
one is wrong
一个是intel公司创建的
the one was created by Intel
也是intel用的
it's the syntax that Intel uses
另一个是由AT&T创建的
another one created by AT&T
至少被称为AT&T语法
or at least it's called the AT&T syntax
告诉我你上次用AT&T芯片是什么时候
tell me when was the last time you used an AT&T chip
这应该就说明了
and that should tell you
哪种语法是合适的
which is the correct assembly format to use
请不要使用AT&T汇编格式
please don't use AT&T assembly format
它很令人困惑
it's confusing
不适合用它
it's just the wrong way to go
请用intel格式
use intel
这些都是intel汇编格式
so this is all an Intel Assembly format
本课程都采用intel格式
the rest of the course will be an Intel Assembly format
请用合适的格式
please use the right format
总之，intel汇编格式中
anyways in Intel Assembly format
数据主要从右流向左
data flows mostly right to left
视频是镜像的
i'm mirrored in the video
从右到左
so right to left
我们来看第一个例子
so we take in the first example
RBX在这里
RBX that's here
把它放到rax中
and we move it into rax
好的
boom nice and simple
这和C语言相符
this makes sense in c
可以写成rax = RBX
you would write rax equals RBX right
这是一个内存访问
okay this this is a memory access
取RBX
we take RBX
加4
we add four to it
能得到一个数字
this gives us a number
访问该数字指向的内存地址
we look in memory at the location reference by that number
如果rbx中是80,000
if that number is if rbx is 80,000
然后加上4
and we add four to it
是80004
we look at 80,004
从这里加载8字节
we load 8 bytes out of that
即64位
64 bits
我们把它
and we put it
我们把它放到rax
we move it into rax
这里注意一点
there's a little bit of magic in this statement
它是如何知道要加载8字节的
in that it knows to load 8 bytes
因为rax的长度是8字节
because rax is 8 bytes long
也可以显示指出要加载的大小
you can also explicitly give sizes
但
but again
这里是复习
this is a high level review
如果你不知道如何显示指定大小
if you don't know how to do that
可先学学汇编
please go learn assembly
然后是加法指令
add arithmetic instructions
你可以将rbx加到rax中
you can of course take RBX add it to rax
等一下
wait a second
我一直指反了
i've been going backwards whole time
你可以取出rbx值，加上rax值，存在rax中
you can take RBX add it to RAX and store it in RAX
等价于c中的rax += rbx
this is basically RAX plus equals RBX in the c equivalent
这里就是错误的地方了
this is where my embarrassing mistake is
mul是乘数指令
mul is a multiplier a multiplication
它只需要接收一个寄存器参数
it only takes actually one register argument
它会将其与rax相乘
it multiplies whatever is an rax by the argument
并将超过64位的值放到rdx中
and also stores the overflow in rdx
所以这里的rdi没用
so this ignored this rdi
这就是rax = rax * rsi
this will do rax equals rax times rsi
当然2个64位数字的乘法
and of course multiplication of 2 64 bit numbers
能产生比64位大得多的数字
can produce a much larger number than 64 bits
所有的溢出都放入RDX
all that overflow goes into rdx
inc rax使RAX自增1
inc RAX increments rax by one
inc一个rax指向的内存地址
inc the memory location pointed to by rax
会让该内存地址中的值自增1
increments the value in that memory
这里是复习
this should all be a review
只有几个数据操作的例子
just a couple of high level examples on what data manipulation instructions can look like
我忘了
i forgot
我应该加上一个数据存储的指令
i should have probably put in a data store instruction
这个从内存读出数据
this reads data from memory
如果把这两个操作数反过来
if you just reverse these two operands
将把rax的值写入rbx+4指向的内存
you will be writing rax into rbx + 4
我们继续
let's move on
控制流程指令
control flow instruction
控制流由条件与无条件跳转决定
so control flow is determined by conditional and unconditional jumps
和c语言中的if语句一样
same way you have an if statement in c
c语言中的if语句
or when you have an if statement in c
会编译成条件、无条件跳转
gets compiled into some conditional unconditional jumps
函数调用
if you have a function call
会编译成call指令
gets compiled into a call instruction
函数返回
when you return
会编译成ret指令
that's a ret instruction
x86或AMD64汇编，支持许多种条件跳转
x86 or AMD64 assembly supports a number of conditional jump types
有符号可以跳转（js）
you can jump if something is signed
无符号也可跳转（jns）
so negative you can jump
如果两个值相等
if two values are equal
一般先执行比较指令，然后跳转指令
and generally you do a comparison and then the jump
比如这个跳转指令
so if you have this jump
这里的jb表示低于某个值就跳转
jb means jump if below right here
这是jl，的无符号版跳转指令
this is an unsigned less than as opposed to less than which is signed
待会会讲到补码，以及有无符号
we'll talk about two's complement and signed and unsigned toward then
这里只是低于某个值就跳转
so this says jump below some location
但低于什么值呢
but jump below what
这里没有任何条件
there's no condition here
但实际上在此之前已经比较了，并保存了结果
well the conditions actually checked earlier and saved
然后该跳转指令再使用它
and this the conditional jump uses it right
我们看看原理
let's see how this works
实际上有一个特殊的寄存器叫标志寄存器
there's actually a special register called the flags register
x86、amd64和arm上都有
it exists on x86 on AMD64 on arm
这个寄存器有一堆标志位
and this register has a bunch of single bit flags
算数操作指令会修改它
that are updated by arithmetic operations
以及几个其他类型的指令
and certain other types of instructions
举个例子
so for example
amd64中的cmp指令
the compare instruction in amd64
它会做一个减法
it does a subtraction
丢弃结果
discards the result
但会修改各种标志位
but updates the various flags
例如，ZF标志位结果是0
the flags are for example the zero flag is the result zero
所以cmp rax rbx
so cmp rax rbx
如果rax和RBX相等
if rax and rbx are equal
ZF将被置为1
the zero flag will be set to one
之后比较是否相等的je
then a resulting je for jump if they were equal
会检查ZF是否为1
checks if the zero flag is one
很简单对吧
fairly straightforward right
这就是它的工作原理
and that's how it works
通过组合起这些标志位
and by combining these different flags
可以区分很多不同的条件
you can actually tell a lot of different conditions
如果执行rax - rbx
so if you do an rax minus rbx
用cmp，或sub指令
with a compare or with a subtract
如果不想丢弃计算结果的话
if you don't want to discard the result
你也可以这样做
you can also do that
这会设置SF位和ZF位
it'll set you know the sign flag and the zero flag
你可以查看，比如 jle的跳转条件
you can look for conditions where for example jump less than or equal
ZF要是1
the zero flag should be one
或者 SF不等于OF
or the sign flag is not equal to the overflow flag
我不打算仔细研究它的含义
i'm not gonna go through and examine the meaning of this
因为这也需要我做一些准备
because also it takes a little bit of preparation on my part
但是如果你感兴趣的话
but if you're interested
你可以去深入了解这些
you can go read further into this
这是进行条件检查和跳转的一种聪明方法
it's a fairly clever way of doing these sort of conditional checks and jumps
这就是条件控制在x86、amd64、arm等架构中的工作方式
that's how conditional control flow works in x86 amd64 arm and so forth
arm有点不同
i mean arm is a little different
但概念是一样的
but concept is the same
最后
finally
我们要讨论的最后一种指令是
i think this the last type of instruction we'll talk about
系统调用
is system calls
所有程序都必须与外部交互
all programs have to interact with the outside world
这主要是通过系统调用完成的
and this is done primarily via system calls
每次互动都是这样进行的
so each interaction is done this way
每个系统调用
each system call
系统调用会调用os功能
a system call is a dispatch into operating system functionality
就是程序叫os为它做点事
where the program asks the operating system to do something for it
触发系统调用时
when you trigger a system call
程序停止
your program stops
os内核接管控制权，完成请求内容
the OS kernel takes control carries out the request
然后返回控制权给程序
and then returns to your program
amd64上使用系统调用要，设置rax为目标系统调用号
on amd64 you create a system call by setting rax to a system call number
根据调用约定将参数存储在rdi、rsi等中
by storing arguments in rdi rsi etc according to the calling convention
稍后我们会讨论调用约定
we'll talk more about calling convention in a sec
再使用syscall指令
and by using the syscall instruction
就好了
and boom
如果你想在外部调试
then from outside if you wanna debug
系统调用使用有问题的shellcode
shellcode that's doing system calls incorrectly
你可以使用strace
you can use strace
我展示一下这大概是什么样的
so let me show you what that might look like
到了
here we are
我再放上一个屏幕视图
actually let me bring on up another view
好了
there we go
右上方的这个
this over here on the top right
是Linux系统调用表
is the linux syscall table
它是Ryan A Chapman维护的
as maintained by the great Ryan A Chapman
Ryan A Chapman做的这个表
Ryan A Chapman contributed this to the world
我几乎每天都看它
and i look at it almost every day
这张表列出了Linux所有的系统调用
it is a table of all of the system calls in Linux
有一些老的版本，现在来说比较老的
as of some old, relatively old now, version
还是很有用的
but still relevant
还有他们各种各样的参数等等
and their various arguments and so forth
下一张幻灯片上有链接
i have it linked on the next slide
我们看一眼下一张幻灯片
but actually let's go to the next slide
所以
so
如果你想查看，链接就在下方这里
the link is right down here if you want to follow along
有很多系统调用
there are a lot of syscalls
我这里主要演示exit
i'm gonna demonstrate mostly the exit syscall right now
之后可能还会展示几个
and then maybe a couple of other ones later
但你应该了解这些系统调用
but honestly you should know all this
我们也可能不会展示更多
maybe we won't demonstrate them
我们看一个简单程序
let's look at a simple program that we're gonna write from scratch
我已经写好了
that i actually already wrote from scratch
就叫exit
called exit
有一些汇编的样板模式
there're some boiler plate for the assembler
这个表示，程序入口就在这里
it says okay the started entry point is gonna be right here
有一个全局符号叫入口点
there is a global symbol called an entry point
就在这里
it's gonna be right here
我们用的Intel语法
we're using Intel syntax
我们可以用GCC编译它
and we can just compile this with gcc
或者你汇编它
or you can also just assemble it and so forth
可以用gcc的子组件
with different sub components of gcc
我们就用整个gcc
but we just use the big gcc
不要链接libc
we have to not link in libc
好的
all right
现在我们可以执行它了
and now we can just execute it
它会做什么
so what does this do
它将rax设为60
it moves 60 to rax
60号系统调用是什么
what is syscall 60
它表示exit
syscall 60 is exit
它通过rdi接收一个参数
and it takes one argument through rdi
这个参数是错误码
which is the error code
这个参数我们给了它42
that argument we gave it 42
如果我们检查返回值
so if we do check the return value
这是在bash中检查前一个程序返回值的方法
this is how you check the return value of the previous program in bash
就是这个
there it is
我们也可以strace看一下
we can also strace this
能看到做了些设置
and we can see that it does some set up
不知道什么时候发生的
wherever that happens
然后执行了exit
and then it does the exit
酷
cool so
有趣的是
it's interesting that oh
这编译成了一个so
so this is a shared object
看一下
let me see
能这样吗
can we do this
没问题
that's right
这样它就执行了exit
boom all it does is exit
很棒
awesome cool
好吧
okay
取决于你看这些视频的顺序
so depending on the order you watch these videos
你可能已经知道为什么会这样
you might understand what happened here
看了Linux进程生命周期，你就会知道
in the Linux process lifecycle you will understand
为什么它和它不一样
why this was different from this
就是因为它和它的差异
because of the difference between this and that
具体来说是它
specifically that
我们继续
let's roll onwards
好吧
all right
这就是系统调用
so that was system calls
我们接着看看内存
let's move on to memory
我要讲的是几种不同类型的内存
i'm gonna go at a very high level of several different types of memory
但主要讲的是栈
but really mostly is gonna cover the stack
在amd64和大多数现代架构中
so in amd64 and most modern architectures
内存中有一个地方叫栈
there's a place in memory called the stack
负责存储一些东西
which is responsible for storing a number of things
它存储了
it stores the
稍等
hold on hold on
稍等一下，我马上回来
one second i'll be right back
好的，很抱歉
okay sorry about that
我回来了
i am back all right
内存
so memory
栈实现了许多功能
this stack fulfills a number of functions
你应该已经注意到了
you should already notice
如果没有
if you do not
请查阅并研究栈在x86汇编中的作用
please go look up and study what the stack does in a x86 assembly
它记录了函数调用栈
essentially it tracks the call stack
所以无论何时你调用一个函数
so whenever you call a function
要返回到的指令的地址，即返回地址
the return address to the instruction that that function should return to
会被压入栈
gets pushed onto the stack
函数返回时
and when you return from a function
返回地址会从栈中弹出
it gets popped off of the stack
栈还包含了局部变量
the stack also contains local variables
这就要说到基指针和栈帧指针了
that's where the base pointer and the frame pointer
或者说基指针寄存器bp和栈指针寄存器sp
or the base pointer and the stack pointer come in
它俩会记录当前栈帧
to track where in the stack you currently are
在栈里的起始位置与终止位置
and where in the stack your current function kind of ends its allocated space
栈提供了一些空间
the stack provides some scratch space
来缓解寄存器耗尽的问题
to alleviate register exhaustion
该问题大多存在于x86架构
again more of an issue on x86
但由于调用约定，还是会省着用寄存器
but you still save off a lot of registers because of calling conventions
我们马上就会讨论调用约定
as we'll discuss in a second
在其他架构上也是如此
on other architectures as well
当然还是会经常遇到寄存器耗尽的问题
and you of course run into register exhaustion everywhere still
x86架构
and the stack on x86 is always
32位x86架构上，只用栈传参
on 32 bit x86 is always used to pass function arguments
其他架构上
on other architecture
有很多参数的话，还是会用到栈传参
it is still used to pass arguments to functions that take a lot of arguments
amd64上的相关寄存器是RSP和RBP
all right relevant registers on amd64 is RSP and RBP
相关的指令是push和pop
relevant instructions push and pop
push会往栈上写数据
push write something to the stack
pop从栈上读出数据
pop reads it off of the stack
你应该已经知道栈是反方向增长的
you should already know that the stack grows backwards
对于栈，我的展示方式是从右到左
the way that i demonstrate the stack is right to left
内存从大到小，展示的方式是从右往左
the way i demonstrate memory in class is right to left
而栈顶是向左增长的
and the stack grows to the left
最左为0
left is zero
最右边是十六进制的FFFFFFFF
right is ffffffff in hexadecimal
这是历史原因导致的
it is the reason for that is other historical oddities
但现在就是这样
but that's where we are today all right
我们来看看其他类型的内存
let's move on to other types of memory
我意思是内存还是就这么一大块
i mean it's all one big memory
amd64不分段
amd64 is not segmented
没有特殊内存之类的
there are no special memories or anything like that
但有些内存不是用于栈的
but memories used for other things than the stack
我们会在之后的模块讨论动态分配内存
we'll talk about dynamically allocated memory in a future module
你还没必要为此担心
you don't necessarily have to worry about it yet
但它的特性很明显
but it will feature very prominently
某种程度来说，内存可以按意愿来映射，去映射
memory can be mapped unmapped more or less at will
并且在一般的程序中经常这样
and is frequently in normal operational program
你还可以将文件映射到内存中
you can also have files mapped into memory
讲Linux进程生命周期中的共享内存时，我会讨论一下它
i'll discuss that a little bit in terms of shared memory in the Linux lifecycle lecture
这也是基础系列的内容
that's also in this fundamentals series
要记住的一件事是
one thing to keep in mind is that
大多数现代架构中
on most modern architectures
数据是反序存储的
data is stored backwards
如果你有一个8位的
as in if you have an 8 bit
8字节的数字
an 8 byte integer
如一二三四
that is one two three four
0x 01 02 03 04
它不是
which is not
抱歉，我累了
ugh sorry i'm tired ugh
等一下，我喝杯水
let me get a drink of water one sec
好吧，我回来了，抱歉
all right i'm back sorry about that
该讲端序了
so endianess again
我们快速复习一下
let's really quickly cover this
如果要存储这个值
if you were to store the value
0x01234567
到内存地址0x100
at memory location 0x100
在x86或arm的默认配置中
in x86 or default configurations of arm
或现代的MIPS、PBC的默认配置
or modern defaults on MIPS and PBC even now
它将被反序存储为0x67 45 23 01
it would get stored backwards  as 0x67 45 23 01
以字节为单位反序存储
so the bytes are reversed
不是位，是字节
not the bits the bytes
为什么会这样
why does this happen
有很多可能的理论
there's a number of potential theories
一种观点是
one idea is historically
以前的算法通常更关心最低有效位
you were interested in the least significant bits more frequently in algorithms
我不知道这是不是真的
i don't know if this is true
而且以前的内存都是串行的非常慢的介质
and because memory used to be read sequentially out of very slow medium
比如纸带、鼓之类的
such as punch cards or drums or something like that
这样先读取最低有效位计算的更快
it was faster to get at the early memory at the least significant bits first
我不知道这是不是真的
i don't know if that's true
我在什么地方读到过
i read that somewhere
也读到过这样的观点，这样更容易处理不同的大小
i've also read arguments that it is easier to address different sizes
例如，在一个数组中
for example in an array
如果你想读出某个元素
if you want to read something
将其转换成char或short
cast something to a char or a short
这样更容易计算
it just much easier to make that calculation
它就位于该值的内存空间的开头的话
if it is at the beginning of the memory space for the value
我还听说它使向后兼容变得更容易
i've also heard that it made backwards compatibility easier
真正的原因是什么
what are the real reasons
我肯定他们就在网上的某处
i'm sure they're out there somewhere
但他们不在这里
but they're not in this lecture
这里就是几种猜想
but a couple of speculations are in this lecture
接着讲下一个概念
let's move on to the next concept
符号表示
signedness
这是一个棘手的问题
so there's this tricky question
应该如何存储一个数字是正的还是负的
of how to store the fact that a number is positive or negative
之前看了一个指令
i showed you an instruction that
add rax rbx
said add rax RBX
rax是正数还是负数
is rax a positive number rax a negative number
谁知道呢
who knows
我们该怎么指定
or how do we specify
一个想法是
so one idea
一个早期的想法是使用一个符号位
an early idea was to use a signed bit
所以
so you say okay
寄存器的最高位
you have the first bit in a register or whatever or in any value
表示该值是正的还是负的
says whether it's negative or positive
我们举一个8位的例子
let's have an example here with 8 bits
它就在幻灯片上
we have it on the slide
这个00...11表示+3
this all zeros followed by 11 is a positive 3
这个100...11表示-3
and 1 followed by 0 followed by 11 would be a -3
这有一些缺点
so this has a number of drawbacks
一个缺点是
one drawback is that
现在0有了两种不同的表示方法
you now have two different representation for zero
+0 和 -0
a positive zero and a negative zero
这在数学上很奇怪
this is mathematically weird
这使很多数学运算变得复杂
and it complicates a lot of math
另一个缺点是
another drawback
所有的操作都要
is that all of your operations have to be
你好，咪咪
hello
我的猫走了进来
my cat walked back in
所有的操作都要注意符号
all your operations have to be signedness aware
这很糟糕
this is bad
因为这样必须复杂化
because you have to complicate
加法、减法等的实现
the implementation of every add every subtract etc
如你所见
as you can see
根据
depending on
这有一个bug，没问题
there's a bug in oh yeah
如你所见
as you can see
对于8位的无符号数
for an unsigned 8 bit value
如果以255加1
if you add a 1 to 255
会得到0
you end up with a zero
如果是有符号的
if it's signed
-127（和前面255是同一个值）加1
you add a one to negative 127
却要是-126
you have with negative 126
而且不能都按有符号的处理
and you also don't want to have everything being signed
因为这样能表示的值的范围将大大减小
because you lose quite a lot of range
相比于不这样的话
that you would be able to express otherwise
因为这个符号位，将丢失一半的范围
you lose half of it to that signed bit
一个聪明但很疯狂的想法是补码
so a clever but very crazy idea is what's called 2's complement
这个想法是这样的
the idea is this
0只有一种表示形式
we have one representation of 0
如果用它减去1
if you subtract one from that
无符号的话，会得到-1
you get -1 if you are in unsigned world
抱歉，有符号，会得到-1
or sorry -1 if you're in signed world
无符号，则是255
or 255 if you're in unsigned world
它们都是0xff
both of them use 0xff
二进制表示为8个1
as in the 8 bit repentation all ones in binary right
如果再减去1
if you subtract one from that
会得到二进制11111110
you get in binary 11111110
或者十六进制的0xfe
or in hexadecimal 0xfe
它是-2
that's negative two now right
这样做的好处是
the advantage of this
算术运算不用在意符号
is that arithmetic operations don't have to be sign aware
0也只有一种表示方法了
and we have one zero again
所以
right so
0xff加1也是一样的
adding a one to 0xff is the same
不管0xff代表255还是-127
regardless of whether 0xff represents 255 or -127
在这个例子中是-1
or in actually in this case -1
缺点是有点疯狂
the disadvantage is it's a little crazy
这让你觉得有点奇怪
it's a little bit weird to wrap your head around
看视频前你应该已经理解它了
you should have already had your head wrapped around it
但处理负数是有点麻烦
but it's kind of a pain dealing with the values of negative numbers
一直到你适应它前
until you learn to adapt
补码的好处是
the benefit of 2's complement is
我们通常只要在比较时关心符号
we usually only have to really care about signedness during conditional checks
它是通过标志寄存器的SF位
and that's done if you recall using the signed bit
配合特定的条件跳转指令
for and the specific conditional jump of
jl，而不是jb
jump less than instead of jump below
jl是有符号的
less than is signed
jb是无符号的
below is unsigned
很好，看看我们还有什么
cool see what else we got
调用约定
calling conventions
我们快结束了
we're getting close to the end
通话约定很重要
calling conventions are important
因为当你调用一个函数
because when you call a function
传递参数
you pass arguments
会按照一个约定俗成的方式
according to some agreed upon way
在x86，会把参数反序压入栈
on x86 you push arguments in reverse order to the stack
再调用函数
and then you call
这会将函数返回地址压入栈
which pushes the return address onto the stack
函数返回时
and when the function returns
它会把返回值放在eax中
it puts the return value in eax
这是x86的标准调用约定
this is the standard calling convention of x86
还有其他的
there are other ones
这是典型的linux x86 stdcall调用约定
this is like the the typical Linux x86 stdcall calling convention
稍等
hold on
咪咪，我录像呢
petrie i'm trying to record here
我的猫相当老了
my cat is fairly old
都爬不上沙发
and has trouble climbing onto the couch
对这个插曲我很抱歉
anyways sorry about that
我们不会用32位的x86
we're not gonna be using 32 bit x86
它太老派了
it's old school
基本没啥理由用它
there's no reason to ever interact with it not really
我们会用amd64
so we will be using amd64
Linux它的调用约定
the calling convention in Linux for
第一个参数放在rdi
at least is first argument in RDI
第二个放在rsi
second argument in RSI
第三个放在rdx
third argument in RDX
第四个放在rcx
fourth in RCX
然后是r8 r9
then r8 r9
好了
boom you go
返回地址放到栈上
return address gets put on the stack
然后当函数返回时
and then when the function returns
返回值会放入rax
the return value is put into rax
arm有点区别
arm is actually a little interesting
arm有个专门的寄存器放返回地址
arm has a register where it puts the return address
不会把它放到栈上
instead of putting it on the stack
重要的是他们会遵循这些约定
but the point is there are these conventions they're followed
实际上
actually
返回地址放哪里
where the return address goes
不是调用约定的一部分
is not part of a calling convention
它是架构的一部分
it's part of the architecture
它是call指令负责的
it's what the call instruction does
但返回值是
but where the return value is
它是调用约定的一部分
is part of the calling convention
很重要的是，寄存器是共享于函数间的
it's very important to understand that registers are shared between all functions
当然，是在同一个进程，实际上是同一个线程中
essentially in your process in your in your thread actually
这意味着
this means that
如果在main函数中用了一堆寄存器
when if you're using a bunch of registers in your main function
然后调用到libc
and you call into libc
Libc也需要使用寄存器
libc needs to use registers too
它假设它可以随意地使用某些寄存器
and it assumes that it can use certain registers haphazardly
有一份协议规定了
there's a contract an agreement
某些寄存器是调用方负责保存的
where certain registers are caller saved
某些寄存器是被调方负责保存的
certain registers are callee saved
这是调用约定的一部分
this is part of the calling convention
在amd64
on amd64
RBX RBP r12 r13 r14和r15是所谓的被调方负责的
RBX RBP r12 r13 r14 and r15 are what's called callee save
如果你的代码调用了一个库函数
if your code calls into a library function
编译器会确保
the compiler will make sure
调用函数前，你的代码会将这些寄存器保存在栈上（口误）
that your code saves those registers on the stack before making the call
其他所有的寄存器
all other registers
抱歉，说反了
the sorry the other way around
这些寄存器
all these registers are ones
不应该被调用的代码直接更改
that should not be messed with by code that you call
所以当调用进libc时
so when you call into libc
如果libc需要使用这些寄存器
if libc needs to use these registers
RBX RBP等等
rbx rbp and so forth
它会先保存它们
it will save them
再使用
it will use them
再在返回前恢复它们
and then it will restore them before returning
所有其它的寄存器都是可以随便用的
all other registers are up for grabs
它可以随意使用
it can clobber them at will
rax肯定会被改
rax is nearly guaranteed to be clobbered
因为它是用来放返回值的
because that's the return value of the function
我们已经
we've gotten to with Petri's help
我们已经来到了简单复习的尾声
we've gotten to the end of this assembly refresh
我有一些有用的资源
i have a couple of useful resources
一个有趣的是rappel
one interesting resource is rappel
这是一个干爽的
it is a neat
基本呈现给用户的就是一个汇编解释器
basically what appears to the user as an assembly interpreter
我快速地展示一下
let me show this to you real quick
来到终端
here is our terminal so let's
我的终端怎么了
what is going on of my terminal
启动rappel
let's use rappel
这是我们模拟CPU的状态
here's our state of our emulated cpu
有各种标志位
we have our various flags
它们组合起来是这个家伙
and they're here combined into this guy
有寄存器等等
we have our registers and so forth
我可以这样
and here i can do stuff like
结果就在这
and here it is
这是有改变的地方
this is what changed
标红的是有改动的
the red is what changed
我可以test rax, rax
i can do stuff like test rax rax
好的
okay
什么也没变
nothing changed
如果试试test rbx, rbx
if i test rbx rbx
这会执行一个按位与
this does a bitwise and
并更新标志位
and updates flags
ZF标志位变了
i have stored the zero flag
因为RBX等于0
because RBX is 0
能看到test导致ZF变成1了
and we can see that test results in zf being one
rappel有一些限制
rappel has some limitations
能注意到rip看起来毫无道理
you'll notice rip doesn't seem to make sense at all
一开始是400000
it started out at 400000
这很好
that's fine
开始可以是二进制文件模拟加载的任意地址
it can start out wherever the binary that it's emulating is loaded
但它一直保持地址为
but it keeps basically being equal to
400000加上刚执行指令的大小
the 400 plus the size of the instruction you just executed
它所做的就是，把指令汇编一下
what it does is it assembles your instruction
把它放在内存中
puts it there in memory
执行它
executes it
然后停止
and stops afterwards
弄清楚一条指令到底做什么是非常有用的
it's very useful to figure out what exactly an instruction does
我在努力回忆怎么
i'm trying to remember how to
是的，它有个帮助命令
yeah it has some help commands
例如，你可以读写内存
you can for example read and write memory
我展示一下
and let me show you
实际上，如果我们把这个写入rax
actually if we move this into rax
再将rax压入栈
push rax onto the stack
我们来读一下
and let's read
由于某种原因，RSP指向33
rsp is pointed to 33 for some reason
我们从这里读8字节
let's read from this 8 bytes
有东西崩了
something broke
也许它没有映射
maybe it's not mapped
是的，它没有映射
yeah it is not mapped
事实上，由于某种原因
in fact for some reason
RSP出错了
rsp got messed up
rappel与这里的栈出了点状况
something is weird with rappel and the stack possibly
总之，你能在这里试试汇编指令
anyways you can play around with assembly instructions
比如，可以试试mul
you can do for example my awesome mul
如果我们
so if we
我展示下，mul的结果会放到rax中
i will show you that rax is what mul ends up going into
把1放到rax
so if we do put one into rax
42放到rsi
and 42 into rsi
然后执行mul rsi
and we do mul rsi
你看，这是42
you see this is 42
所以幻灯片上是错的
so the slides were wrong
mul只需要一个寄存器参数
mul just takes one register cool
这差不多就是我要展示的全部内容
this is more or less all that i have for you for
汇编复习的全部内容
i mean it is all that i have for you for the assembly refresher
注意
remember
这应该是一个复习
this should have been a refresher
要学好这门课，你应该了解汇编
you should know assembly to do well in this course
你将会写汇编
you're going to have to write it
读汇编
you're going to have to read it
你会从头写它
you're going to have to make it appear out of thin air
在其他复杂的情况下
in otherwise complicated scenarios
所以请确保你会汇编
so make sure you know assembly
我们将会在后续课程再见
i will see you later in this foundation series and in the rest of the course
晚安
good night